Guide to the Leicester Craig Clark Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Leicester Craig Clark Family Papers
1829-1928
MS 1137
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9
(16 boxes)
Family of descendants of Justin Ely (1739-1817) with branches in Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Ohio. More than half the papers consists of family correspondence and printed matter (1883-1920) collected by Leicester Craig Clark. The printed matter (ca. 1900-1920) includes advertising brochures, greeting cards, picture postcards, and pamphlets from religious and charitable organizations, which offer a sample of American popular culture for the period. Clark's sister, Margaret Clark Neal, and his mother, Bertha Ely Clark, are prominently represented.Another major portion of the papers consists of approximately four hundred photographs (1862-1925) showing members of the related Clark, Ely, Farnam, Kent, Kingsley, and Upham families, their friends, and views of places in Europe and the United States. Most of the photographs were taken by professional photographers. Also included are eighty paintings and drawings made by members of the family, most numerous being the watercolors and oil paintings of Elizabeth Ely. A number of tracings were done by Leicester Craig Clark. Additional memorabilia includes newspaper clippings, programs, invitations, and commonplace books.
Clark, Leicester Craig, 1885-1959
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry W. Farnam, Jr., 1967.
Scope and Contents
Family of descendants of Justin Ely (1739-1817) with branches in Massachusetts, Connecticut, and Ohio. More than half the papers consists of family correspondence and printed matter (1883-1920) collected by Leicester Craig Clark. The printed matter (ca. 1900-1920) includes advertising brochures, greeting cards, picture postcards, and pamphlets from religious and charitable organizations, which offer a sample of American popular culture for the period. Clark's sister, Margaret Clark Neal, and his mother, Bertha Ely Clark, are prominently represented.Another major portion of the papers consists of approximately four hundred photographs (1862-1925) showing members of the related Clark, Ely, Farnam, Kent, Kingsley, and Upham families, their friends, and views of places in Europe and the United States. Most of the photographs were taken by professional photographers. Also included are eighty paintings and drawings made by members of the family, most numerous being the watercolors and oil paintings of Elizabeth Ely. A number of tracings were done by Leicester Craig Clark. Additional memorabilia includes newspaper clippings, programs, invitations, and commonplace books.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: Series I: Justin Ely Family Papers, 1862-1928; Series II: Index to the Photographs; Series III: Leicester Craig Clark Papers
Biographical / Historical
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the Ely family, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Advertising; Drawing -- 19th century; Families; Painting -- United States; Popular culture; Women painters; Albums (Books); Photoprints; Postcards; Artists; Clark, Bertha Kent Ely, b. 1860; Clark, Leicester Craig, 1885-1959; Ely, Elizabeth W., 1815-1837; Neal, Margaret Clark; Clark family; Ely family; Farnham family; Kent family; Kingsley family; Upham family
- JUSTIN ELY FAMILY PAPERS, 1862-1928, undated; Series I; 3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
  - Letters
    - Munson, M., to Martha Upham, 1882 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Olind, Mrs. C., to Mrs. J. Craig Clark, 1923 January 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified to Margaret, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Postcards
    - Yale University and New Haven, Connecticut, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1905-1915, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Greeting cards, 1884-1890, 1909-1913, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Notebook of "Spoken English,", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Printed matter, 1894, 1911-1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Programs, printed invitations, etc., 1884-1926, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Wooden items, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Vestments, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Photographs
    General
    See Index for listing
    - Family members and friends
      - Barton _____, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Bates, Anna Upham, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Bates, Laura and Louise, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Bellamy, Fred, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Bowles, Elizabeth (Belden) (4), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Bowles, Walter, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - C_____, B.R. (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Chambers, Elsie G., undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Cheney, Genevieve H., undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Cheney, Genevieve H., undated (Box 7, Folder 126)
      - [Clark family?], undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Clark, Bertha (2), 1862 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Clark, Bertha (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Clark, Bertha, undated (Box 7, Folder 127)
      - Clark, Bertha Kent (Ely) (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - Clark, J.C., undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Clark, Leicester Craig (7), undated (Box 7, Folder 128)
      - [Clark, Lillie?] (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - [Clark, Lillie?] (3), undated (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - [Clark, Lillie?] (2), undated (Box 7, Folder 129)
      - Clark, Lillie and Bertha (2), 1865 Sep, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Clark, Margaret (11), undated (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
      - Clark, Margaret (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - [Clark, Margaret and Lillie?] (3), undated (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - Clark, Martha Upham (2), undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Cox, Samuel Hanson, 1864 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Ely, Charles, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Ely, Mrs. Charles, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Ely, Charles U. (2), undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Ely, Harriet (Kent), undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Ely, Heman, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Ely, Jessie (Kent) (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Ely, Lizzie U., undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Ely, Louise Wentworth, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Ely, Mary (Day), 1892 August 13 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Ely, Morris U. (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Farnam, Henry W., and family, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Farnam, Henry W., and Louise W., undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Farnam, Julie (Kingsley) (Mrs. Henry W.), undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Farnam, Katherine, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - Farnam, Louise and Katherine, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Farnam, Louise, Katherine, and Henry (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Frothingham, John S., undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Frothingham, Katherine (Kent) (2), undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Greene, Mrs., and Mrs. and Miss Thatcher, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Holbrook,_____ (2), 1873 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Jackson, Mary Crane, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
      - Kingsley, Charles, undated (Box 3, Folder 41)
      - Kingsley, Louise Upham, undated (Box 3, Folder 42)
      - Kingsley, William L., undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - L_____, K., undated (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Lee, John and Sibley, 1893 July (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - Marshall, Harriet Ely, undated (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Munson, Marjory F., undated (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - Rice, Elizabeth, undated (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Robeson, Jack, undated (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - [Saportas?], Gabrielle S. Mathilde, 1878 August 4 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - [Stainack?], Sara Perry (2), 1905 July 14 (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - Stevens, Alexander C., 1907 (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - T_____, E.R., undated (Box 7, Folder 130)
      - Townshend, Arthur B., undated (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Upham, Charlotte, undated (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - Upham, Hannah (2), undated (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - White, Edwin, 1868 February (Box 3, Folder 51)
    - Unidentified
      General note
      Folder No. 90-97
      - "George" (9), 1881, undated (Box 3, Folder 52-54)
      - "Leicester,", 1887 (Box 3, Folder 55)
      - "Meryl,", undated (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - "Ahbuhlea Christmas Party" (2), 1911 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Miscellaneous(42), 1864,1925,undated (Box 3, Folder 57-74)
      - Miscellaneous (35), undated (Box 4, Folder 80-83)
      - Miscellaneous (15), undated (Box 7, Folder 132-136)
    - Other subjects by geographic location
      Folder No. 116
      - Antwerp (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 99)
      - Antwerp, 1869 (Box 8, Folder 137)
      - Athens, undated (Box 8, Folder 138)
      - Constantinople, undated (Box 8, Folder 139)
      - Egypt (2), undated (Box 8, Folder 140)
      - France (23), undated (Box 6, Folder 100-103)
      - France (8), undated (Box 8, Folder 141)
      - Great Britain (5), 1868, undated (Box 6, Folder 104)
      - Great Britain (8), 1874, undated (Box 8, Folder 142)
      - Italy (3), undated (Box 6, Folder 105)
      - Italy (11), undated (Box 8, Folder 143)
      - Jerusalem, undated (Box 8, Folder 144)
      - Moscow, undated (Box 6, Folder 117)
      - Seville, undated (Box 8, Folder 145)
      - Switzerland (2), undated (Box 8, Folder 146)
      - United States
        Folder No. 121-124
        - Black River, Elyria, Ohio (7), undated (Box 6, Folder 118-119)
        - Greenwood Cemetery (2), undated (Box 6, Folder 120)
        - Portsmouth, New Hampshire (6), undated (Box 6, Folder 106-107)
        - St. Luke's Hospital, New York, undated (Box 8, Folder 147)
        - Sophia Street homestead (4), undated (Box 6, Folder 108)
        - Woodbury, Connecticut (6), undated (Box 6, Folder 109)
        - Unidentified (21), undated (Box 6, Folder 110-111)
        - Photograph album of unidentified location, undated (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - Miscellaneous subjects
      Folder No. 125
      - Nurses, undated (Box 7, Folder 131)
      - Red Cross Convention, with President Calvin Coolidge, Washington, D.C. (2), 1923 September (Box 5, Folder 98)
      - Works of art (4), undated (Box 6, Folder 113)
      - Works of art (33), undated (Box 8, Folder 148)
      - Unidentified (11), undated (Box 6, Folder 114-115)
      - Unidentified (12), undated (Box 8, Folder 149)
  - Drawings, paintings, and tracings, undated (Box 9)
    See also: Box 8 for one oversize painting
- LEICESTER CRAIG CLARK PAPERS, Series II
  - Clark, Bertha Kent Ely
    - Correspondence
      - 1877 - 1914 October (Box 10, Folder 1-14)
      - 1914 October - 1921 (Box 11, Folder 15-28)
      - 1922-1927, undated (Box 12, Folder 29-37)
  - Clark, Leicester Craig
    - Correspondence
      - 1893 - 1908 December (Box 12, Folder 38-41)
      - 1908 December - 1913 October 2 (Box 13, Folder 42-54)
      - 1913 October 3 - 1918 August (Box 14, Folder 55-66)
      - 1918 September - 1925 June (Box 15, Folder 67-79)
      - 1925 July - 1930 (Box 16, Folder 80-90)
      - undated (Box 17, Folder 91-94)
    - Financial papers, 1927-1931, undated (Box 17, Folder 95-98)
  - Others
    - Clark, John Craig, 1892-1909, undated (Box 17, Folder 99-100)
    - Ely, Anna Holbrook Perkins, 1857-1887, undated (Box 17, Folder 101)
    - Ely, Charles Upham, 1837-1850, undated (Box 18, Folder 102)
    - Ely, Eliza Upham, 1849-1918, undated (Box 18, Folder 103-110)
    - Ely, Harriet Kent, 1852-1893, undated (Box 18, Folder 111-112)
    - Ely, Jessie Kent, 1874, undated (Box 18, Folder 113)
    - Ely, Leicester Kent, 1844-1885, undated (Box 19, Folder 114-117)
    - Lee, Bertha Craig Clark, 1905-1927, undated (Box 19, Folder 118)
    - Neal, Margaret Clark, 1902-1919, undated (Box 19, Folder 119)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 19, Folder 120-125)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 20, Folder 126-129)
    - Miscellanea, undated (Box 21, Folder 130-132)